<faq>
	<section>
		<summary>
			Frequently asked questions
	
			This is a list of questions you can expect based on past 
			presentations related to enlightenment. Yes most of these questions 
			are in the faq on the website, but we all know how many end users 
			read that before asking questions.
		</summary>
	</section>
	<section>
		<item>
			<question>
				Is enlightenment development dead?
			</question>
			<answer>
				No, enlightenment has been in constant development since 
				it's inception. We did not release a window manager for 3 years,
				because it was not apriority that the current developers wanted 
				to spend their limited time on. Kim Woelders stepped up and 
				made extensive improvements that called for new releases.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				How many active developers are there?
			</question>
			<answer>
				There are 10 developers making regular commits, and 42 
				developers with CVS access.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				How active is CVS (average time between cvs commits)?
			</question>
			<answer>
				Approximately 1.58 hours between commits. This number is 
				slightly on the high side because of an issue with the 
				commit bot.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				How long until DR17?
			</question>
			<answer>
				No time estimates are given because the code is developed 
				in spare time only. Without a schedule of regular working hours,
				development time is impossible to estimate.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				Why is there so much bloat in E?
			</question>
			<answer>
				Bloat? What bloat? Most claims of bloat in E are from '97 
				or '98, at which time Enlightenment really pushed the boundaries
				of the hardware. These days, E could be considered one of the 
				lighter environments out there, and will happily run on old 
				pentium, or pre-G3 PPC class hardware.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				Why are you making ANOTHER wm like gnome or kde?
			</question>
			<answer>
				Enlightenment pre-dates gnome and kde. It was originally 
				used by gnome as the default window manager. Until recently, 
				Enlightenment focused solely on window management. While there 
				will be some overlap between the EFL and the other environments,
				we aim to work with their applications and environments as much 
				as possible.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				How fast will the new e apps work?
			</question>
			<answer>
				This will depend on the application to a large degree. The 
				overall goal is to make the libraries as fast and flexible as 
				possible, so that apps can target their specific platform.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				How much memory or cpu will the libs use?
			</question>
			<answer>
				As little as possible to accomplish the necessary 
				functionality. At this point, all of the core libraries can run 
				fit into about 1.1 MB of storage. At runtime, the memory use 
				varies depending on architecture and application, but 
				demonstrations have shown the libraries being used on devices 
				with minimal memory.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				Where do the libs run (portability)?
			</question>
			<answer>
				Currently tested platforms include: Linux (x86, powerpc, ARM, 
				Sparc), Solaris, and Mac OS X. Some libraries have been tested 
				on Windows 2000 and CE. Most POSIX compatible environments
				should be easily ported to.
			</answer>
		</item>
		<item>
			<question>
				Why are you redoing a lot of work being done in fd.o?
			</question>
			<answer>
				We're not. The freedesktop group was formed to specify ways that
				applications and libraries can communicate through X. We are 
				making use of these standards where ever it is technically 
				reasonable. In fact, our abstractions may help the fd.o group, 
				as standards groups often require at least 2 separate 
				implementations of a proposal before it is accepted as a 
				standard.
			</answer>
		</item>
	</section>
</faq>
