<!-- EDB & EET Recipes -->

<chapter>
<title>EDB &amp; EET</title>

<para>
EDB is a database convenience library wrapped around the Berkeley DB 2.7.7 by 
Sleepycat Software. It is intended to make accessing database information portable, 
easy, fast and efficient.
</para>

<para>
EET is a tiny library designed to write arbitary chunks of data to a file and 
optionally compress each chunk (very much like a zip file) and allows for fast 
random-access reading of the file later on. It does not do zip as a zip itself 
has more complexity than is needed, and it was much simpler to impliment this once here.
</para>

<para>
EDB provides an excellent method of storing and retrieving application configuration 
information, although it can be used for more extensively than that. 
Ebits, the predecessor to Edje, even used EDB as a container for Ebits themes 
prior to EET. An Edb consists of a series of key/value pairs, which can consist of a 
variety of data types, including integers, floating point values, strings, and binary 
data. The simplified API provides simple, complete, and unified functions for managing 
and accessing your database.
</para>

<para>
In addition to the library, a variety of tools are available to access and 
modify your EDBs. The edb_ed tool provides a simple command line interface that can 
easily be scripted, especially useful for use with the GNU autotools suite. The edb_vt_ed 
tool provides an easy to use curses interface. Finally, edb_gtk_ed provides an elegant 
and easy GUI interface, especially useful for end user editing of configuration 
data contained in EDBs. 
</para>

<para>
Eet is extremely fast, small and simple. Eet files can be very small and highly 
compressed, making them very optimal for just sending across the internet without 
having to archive, compress or decompress and install them. They allow for 
lightning-fast random-acess reads once created, making them perfect for storing 
data that is written once (or rarely) and read many times, but the program does 
not want to have to read it all in at once.
</para>

<para>
It also can encode and decode data structures in memory, as well as image data for 
saving to Eet files or sending across the network to other machines, or just writing 
to arbitary files on the system. All data is encoded in a platform independant way 
and can be written and read by any architecture.
</para>

&edb_shell_file_create;
&edb_intro;
&edb_key_get;

</chapter>

