<!-- Edje EDC Recipes -->

<chapter>
<title>Edje EDC &amp; Embryo</title>

<para>
Edje Data Collections (EDC) source files allow for easy creation of rich and powerful
graphical interfaces.  Your Edje application is divided into two distinct parts, the
application code (using calls from <filename>Edje.h</filename>) and the interface 
description in the EDC.  The only connectivity needed between your interface and
your application code are signals emited by your interface and are recieved by
Edje callbacks in your application code.  
</para>

<para>
An EDC is broken into several major sections describing the images and fonts that are used
in the interface, descriptions of how the various <literal>parts</literal> of the interface are
laid out, and descriptions of actions or <literal>programs</literal> that occur when your interface
is interacted with.  This functionality can be further supplimented by employing Embryo's
scripting language to add C like programability into the Edje EDC itself.
</para>

<para>
The end result of an EDC, including all of it's fonts and images, is a single EET.  Because
the entire interface is made avalible in a single file "theme" distribution is greatly simplified.
</para>

<para>
While Edje EDC's might be considered "themes" they are much more.  A traditional "theme"
is a file or group of files that augment some existing interface by changing the color
of elements or replacing the images that make up the interface itself.  But these 
methods insuffient for really changing the design of an applications interface, limiting
themers from modification and often requiring an application redesign at some point
in order to expand the capabilities of the interface for greater funcationlity.
A GTK application will always look the same, despite what theme it is using.  A simple
example might be that a GTK or QT application will always have a rectangular shape and if
it isn't borderless you can't make it borderless via a theme.  However, an Edje application
could be change from rectangular to an oval shaped border with a simple modification of
the EDC, or could remove and rearrange all of the elements of the interface without ever
touching application code.  In this way Edje allows a far greater ammount of control
and flexablity than provided by any other solution in the Open Source comminity and allows
the Open programing model to be truely leverage to allow even non-programmers (as many themers are)
to contribute and modify things as they see fit.
</para>

&edje_embryo_toggle;
&edje_text_effect_fade;
</chapter>

