<!-- Imlib2 Recipes -->

<chapter>
<title>Imlib2</title>

<para>
Imlib2 is the successor to Imlib. It is not just a newer version - it is a completely 
new library. Imlib2 can be installed alongside Imlib 1.x without any problems since 
they are effectively different libraries - but they Have very similar functionality.
</para>

<para>
Imlib2 can do the following:
</para>

<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
 <listitem><para>Load image files from disk in one of many formats</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Save images to disk in one of many formats</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Render image data onto other images</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Render images to an X-Windows drawable</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Produce pixmaps and pixmap masks of Images</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Apply filters to images</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Rotate images</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Accept RGBA Data for images</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Scale images</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Alpha blend Images on other images or drawables</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Apply color correction and modification tables and factors to images</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Render images onto images with color correction and modification tables</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Render truetype anti-aliased text</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Render truetype anti-aliased text at any angle</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Render anti-aliased lines</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Render rectangles</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Render linear multi-colored gradients</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Cache data intelligently for maximum performance</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Allocate colors automatically</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Allow full control over caching and color allocation</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Provide highly optimized MMX assembly for core routines</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Provide plug-in filter interface</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Provide on-the-fly runtime plug-in image loading and saving interface</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Fastest image compositing, rendering and manipulation library for X</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
If what you want isn't in the list above somewhere then likely Imlib2 does not do it. 
If it does, it likely does it faster than any other library you can find (this includes 
gdk-pixbuf, gdkrgb, etc.) primarily because of highly optimized code and a smart subsystem 
that does the dirty work for you and picks up the pieces for you so you can be lazy and 
let Imlib2 do all the optimizations for you.
</para>

<para>
Imlib2 provides a powerful engine for image manipulation and rendering.  
Using loaders it can handle a variety of image formats including BMP, GIF (via unGIF),
JPEG, PNG, PNM, TGA, TIFF, XPM and more.
</para>

&imlib_watermark;
&imlib_scale;
&imlib_free_rotate;
&imlib_90_rotate;
&imlib_flip;

</chapter>

