<!-- 
 Appendix A.  The tag is kept in the main XML file to allow for inclusion in aux documentation.
  -->
<title>EDC Reference</title>

<programlisting>
//EDC Form
images {
        // Images
}

collections {
   group {
        // Group1 Params

        parts {
                part {
                        // Part Params

                        description {
                                // State Params
                        }

                }
        }

        programs {
                program {
                        // Program Params
                }
        }
     }

   group {
        // Group2 Params
        parts {
        ........
        }
        programs {
        ......
        }
   }
}
</programlisting>


<table frame='topbot'><title>EDC Keyword Reference</title>
<tgroup cols='4' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
<colspec align='right'/>
<colspec align='right'/>
<colspec align='center'/>
<colspec align='left'/>
<thead>
<row>
  <entry>Section</entry>
  <entry>Keyword</entry>
  <entry>Parameters</entry>
  <entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>

<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>images</entry>
  <entry>image,</entry>
  <entry>"image" STORAGE_METHOD;</entry>
  <entry>Where storage method is of the following: COMP for lossless compressed, RAW for lossless uncompressed, or LOSSY for lossy compressed followed by
 the quality level (0-100)
ex: image, "button.png" LOSSY 85;
ex: image, "backdrop.jpg" RAW;</entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>group</entry>
  <entry>name,</entry>
  <entry>"group_name";</entry>
  <entry>Name used to access an individual interface in an EET.</entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>group
        </entry>
  <entry>min,
        </entry>
  <entry>0 0;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integer values specifying minimum horizontal (arg1) and vertical (arg2) size of interface in pixels.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>group
        </entry>
  <entry>max,
        </entry>
  <entry>0 0;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integer values specifying maximum horizontal (arg1) and vertical (arg2) size of interface in pixels.
        </entry>
</row>


<row>
  <entry>part
        </entry>
  <entry>name,
        </entry>
  <entry>"part_name";
        </entry>
  <entry>Symbolic part name, used for later reference in EDC.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>part
        </entry>
  <entry>type,
        </entry>
  <entry>TYPE;
        </entry>
  <entry>Where type is: IMAGE, RECT, TEXT, SWALLOW or NONE.  Defaults to IMAGE if no type is specified.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>part
        </entry>
  <entry>effect,
        </entry>
  <entry>FX_TYPE;
        </entry>
  <entry>Effect type applied to text as rendered by the part. Acceptable FX_TYPEs are: NONE, PLAIN, OUTLINE, SOFT_OUTLINE, SHADOW, SOFT_SHADOW, OUTLINE_SH
ADOW, OUTLINE_SOFT_SHADOW. Default type is NONE.  ex: effect, SOFT_OUTLINE;
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>part
        </entry>
  <entry>mouse_events,
        </entry>
  <entry>0;
        </entry>
  <entry>Boolean value specifying whether the part accepts mouse events or not. No signals are generated from parts that do not accept events.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>part
        </entry>
  <entry>repeat_events,
        </entry>
  <entry>0;
        </entry>
  <entry>Boolean value specifying whether a part repeats an event to the part below it.  When repeat is set to 0 (off, the default) and two parts that accept events
        are on top of each other the top most object will receive the event and not the parts below it, turning repeat to 1 (on) will continue to send the
 event down to
        the next part below it.
        </entry>
</row>


<row>
  <entry>part
        </entry>
  <entry>clip_to,
        </entry>
  <entry>"part";
        </entry>
  <entry>Clip to the size of the specified part. Any amount of the current part that extends beyond the size of the clipped to part will be clipped off.  Clipped text parts
        always truncate the text string to "...".
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>part
        </entry>
  <entry>color_class,
        </entry>
  <entry>"class";
        </entry>
  <entry>Name of color class to apply to the current part.  Color classes are defined in application code.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>part
        </entry>
  <entry>text_class,
        </entry>
  <entry>"class";
        </entry>
  <entry>Name of text class to apply to the current part.  Text classes are defined in application code.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>state,
        </entry>
  <entry>"name" INDEX;
        </entry>
  <entry>Descriptive name for the individual state, the default state must always be named "default". The INDEX value is a double between 0.0 and 1.0 which indicates levels of completion, the default is 0.0. Multiple states can have the same name yet with a different index value.
ex: state, "default" 0.0;
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>visible,
        </entry>
  <entry>0;
        </entry>
  <entry>Boolean value specifying whether part is visable or not. Non-visable parts do not generate events.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>align,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VER_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Specify alignment of the part within its container as specified by rel1/rel2. Values are specified as doubles from 0.0 (align left/top) to 1.0 (
align right/bottom).
ex: align, 0.5 0.5; (Aligns part in center of container)
ex: align, 0.0 1.0; (Aligns part to bottom left of container)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>min,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_SIZE VER_SIZE;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integer values specifying minimum horizontal (arg1) and vertical (arg2) size of part in pixels.
ex: min, 100 100;
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>max,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_SIZE VER_SIZE;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integer values specifying maximum horizontal (arg1) and vertical (arg2) size of part in pixels.
ex: max, 100 100;
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>step,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VERT_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integer stepping values in integer pixels for horizontal (arg1) and vertical (arg2) scaling. When stepping is enabled the width or/and height of 
the image will always be divisable by its stepping value when scaled. Default stepping values are 0 0 (ie: stepping disabled).
ex: step, 20 1 (Image width must always be multple of 20, ie: 0, 20, 40, 60, etc. Height can be any value)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>aspect,
        </entry>
  <entry>MIN MAX;
        </entry>
  <entry>Double min (arg1) and max (arg2) aspect ratio values. This controls the aspect ratio (ratio of width to height) of a scaled part, typically images. The default ratio is 0.0. If both values are the same the ratio is fixed.
ex: aspect, 1.0 5.0; (Minimum aspect of 1:1, maximum of 5:1 - Width:Height);
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>color,
        </entry>
  <entry>RED GREEN BLUE ALPHA;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integer values ranging from 0 to 255 specifying the color of a rectangle or text part.
ex: color, 0 0 0 255; (Part is colored black)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>color2,
        </entry>
  <entry>RED GREEN BLUE ALPHA;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integer values ranging from 0 to 255 specifying the color of a text parts shadow.
ex: color2, 0 0 255 255; (Shadow is blue)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>color3,
        </entry>
  <entry>RED GREEN BLUE ALPHA;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integer values ranging from 0 to 255 specifying the color of a text parts outline.
ex: color3, 255 0 0 255; (Outline is colored red)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>description
        </entry>
  <entry>inherit,
        </entry>
  <entry>"name" INDEX;
        </entry>
  <entry>Inherit the values of the description identified by "name" and INDEX.
  Inherit can only be used <emphasis>after</emphasis> a state is set on the
  current description and can not be used for the default state.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>rel1/rel2
        </entry>
  <entry>relative,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VERT_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Doubles representing the horizontal (arg1) and vertical (arg2) positioning of top left corner (for rel1) or bottom right corner (for rel2) as relative to the part specified by the "to" keyword. If no "to" keyword is present, the values are relative to the corners of the interface.
ex: relative, 0.0 1.0; (For rel1 with no "to": top left corner of part is positioned at the left (0.0), bottom (1.0) corner of the interface.)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>rel1/rel2
        </entry>
  <entry>offset,
        </entry>
  <entry>HORZ_OFF VERT_OFF;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integers specifying deviation in pixels from the position as defined by the relative keyword, both horizontally (arg1) and vertically (arg2).
ex: offset, 5 10; (Position 5 px to the right and 10 px down from the position as stated by the relative keyword)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>rel1/rel2
        </entry>
  <entry>to,
        </entry>
  <entry>"part_name";
        </entry>
  <entry>Specify another part as the reference to be used for the positioning of the current part.
ex: to, "some_part";
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>rel1/rel2
        </entry>
  <entry>to_x,
        </entry>
  <entry>"part_name";
        </entry>
  <entry>Specify another part as the reference to be used for the positioning of the current part. Same as "to", but relativity applies only on the X axis.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>rel1/rel2
        </entry>
  <entry>to_y,
        </entry>
  <entry>"part_name";
        </entry>
  <entry>Specify another part as the reference to be used for the positioning of the current part.  Same as "to", but relativity applies only on the Y axis.
        </entry>
</row>


<row>
  <entry>image
        </entry>
  <entry>normal,
        </entry>
  <entry>"image_name";
        </entry>
  <entry>Name of image to be used.  In an animation, this is the first and last image displayed.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>image
        </entry>
  <entry>tween,
        </entry>
  <entry>"image_name";
        </entry>
  <entry>Name of an image to be used in an animation loop.  Images are dispay in the order they are listed.  There is no limit to the number of tweens that can be specified.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>image
        </entry>
  <entry>border,
        </entry>
  <entry>LEFT RIGHT TOP BOTTOM;
        </entry>
  <entry>Border scaling values for an image part as specified in integer pixel widths, for each four sides of an image. This will stop Edje from scaling the outside edge of an image when scaling an image part.
ex: border, 10 10 10 10; (Scale the edge of the image part 10 pixels on all sides)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>fill
        </entry>
  <entry>smooth,
        </entry>
  <entry>0;
        </entry>
  <entry>Boolean value determining whether scaled images will be smoothed, 0 for no, 1 for yes.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>fill { origin
        </entry>
  <entry>relative,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VERT_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Doubles representing the horizontal (arg1) and vertical (arg2) position from which a fill (tile) should start within it's container as defined by
 rel1/rel2.  Tiling
        then occurs in all directions from that point of origin.  This is similar in use to relativity by rel1 except that it is relative to the parts container rather than
        the whole interface.
        ex: relative, 0.5 0.5; (part starts tiling from the middle of it's container)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>fill { origin
        </entry>
  <entry>offset
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VERT_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integers specifying a pixel offset horizontally (arg1) and vertically (arg2) from the relative position specified by origin{relative,}.  This is 
similar in use to
        offset used in rel1.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>fill { size
        </entry>
  <entry>relative,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VERT_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Doubles representing the horizontal (arg1) and vertical (arg2) position of the bottom right corner of a fill (tile).  This is similar in use to relativity by rel2 except that it is relative to the parts container rather than the whole interface.
        ex: relative, 1.0 1.0; (Tile fills entire space)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>fill { size
        </entry>
  <entry>offset,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VERT_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Integers specifying a pixel offset horizontally (arg1) and vertically (arg2) from the relative position specified by size{relative,}.  This is similar in use to offset
        used in rel2.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>text
        </entry>
  <entry>text,
        </entry>
  <entry>"some string";
        </entry>
  <entry>Text string to be rendered.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>text
        </entry>
  <entry>font,
        </entry>
  <entry>"font_name";
        </entry>
  <entry>Font used for text, where "font_name" is the name of the font file minus its extension.  The path to the font is determined by your applications
        evas font path. ex: font, "Impact"; (Font used is Impact.ttf found in the evas font path)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>text
        </entry>
  <entry>size
        </entry>
  <entry>12;
        </entry>
  <entry>Font size in points.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>text
        </entry>
  <entry>fit,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VERT_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Boolean values specifying whether to scale text to fill its container horizontally (arg1) and/or vertically (arg2).  Default is 0 0;
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>text
        </entry>
  <entry>min,
        </entry>
  <entry>HOR_VAL VERT_VAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Boolean values specifying whether the current text string should define the minimum size of the part, such that all future changes to the text string can
        be no smaller both horizontally (arg1) and vertically (arg2).
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>text
        </entry>
  <entry>align,
        </entry>
  <entry>0.5 0.5;
        </entry>
  <entry>Alignment of text within its containers is defined by rel1/rel2, horizontally (arg1) and vertically (arg2).
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>program
        </entry>
  <entry>name,
        </entry>
  <entry>"prog_name";
        </entry>
  <entry>Symbolic name of program as a unique identifier.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>program
        </entry>
  <entry>signal,
        </entry>
  <entry>SIGNAL;
        </entry>
  <entry>Specifies signal(s) that should cause the program to run.  The signal received must match the specified source to run. Signals may be globbed, but 
only
one signal keyword per program may be used.
        ex: signal, "mouse,clicked,*"; (clicking any mouse button that matches source starts program)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>program
        </entry>
  <entry>source,
        </entry>
  <entry>"signal-source";
        </entry>
  <entry>Source of accepted signal.  Sources may be globbed, but only one source keyword per program may be used.
        ex: source, "button-*"; (Signals from any part or program named "button-*" are accepted)
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>program
        </entry>
  <entry>action,
        </entry>
  <entry>ACTION (param1) (param2);
        </entry>
  <entry>Action to be performed by the program.  Valid actions are: STATE_SET, ACTION_STOP and SIGNAL_EMIT.  Only one action can be specified per program.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>program
        </entry>
  <entry>transition,
        </entry>
  <entry>TYPE LENGTH;
        </entry>
  <entry>Defines how transistions occur using STATE_SET action.  Where type is the style of the transistion and length is a double specifying the number of
        seconds in which to preform the transistion.  Valid types are: LINEAR, SINUSOIDAL, ACCELERATE, and DECELERATE
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>program
        </entry>
  <entry>target,
        </entry>
  <entry>"action-target";
        </entry>
  <entry>Program or part on which the specified action acts.  Multiple target keywords may be specified, one per target.  SIGNAL_EMITs do not have targets.
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>program
        </entry>
  <entry>after,
        </entry>
  <entry>"next-program";
        </entry>
		<entry>Specifies a program to run after the current program completes.  The source and signal parameters of a program run as an "after" are ignored.  Multiple "after" statements can be specified per program.
        </entry>
</row>

</tbody>

</tgroup>
</table>

