<chapter>
<title>The Edje API: Putting your interface to work</title>

<para>
The API for Edje is simple and easy to use.  It should be noted from the outset that the API is designed to be restrictive.  If you
can not accomplish something in code that you want to do it will almost always mean that you should have done it in the EDC.  This design
ensures that even a lazy programmer doesn't deminish the power of an independant interface as designed by Edje.
</para>

<para>
The Edje API includes an initialization function, time related functions, external object functions, and object functions for manipulating
and interfacing with your EET as created using EDC.  Most commonly used will be the object functions, which provide the ability to add
Edje interfaces as an EVAS object and modify animation cycles, resize, get or set values from text parts, define color classes, define
and delete callbacks based on signals from your EET, and even emit signals that get sent back to your EET to trigger events.
Lets look at a simple example of using Edje in your application, using Ecore and EVAS:
</para>

<screen>
/* gcc `edje-config --cflags --libs` `ecore-config --cflags --libs` example.c -o example */
/* A sample EDC can be had here: http://www.cuddletech.com/edje/edc/crossfade.edc */
#include &lt;Ecore_Evas.h&gt;
#include &lt;Ecore.h&gt;
#include &lt;Edje.h&gt;

int app_signal_exit(void *data, int type, void *event);

        /* GLOBALS */
        Ecore_Evas  *   ee;
        Evas        *   evas;
        Evas_Object *   edje;

        double   edje_w, edje_h;


int main(int argv, char *argc[]){

        ecore_init();
        ecore_event_handler_add(ECORE_EVENT_SIGNAL_EXIT, app_signal_exit, NULL);

        ecore_evas_init();
   ee = ecore_evas_software_x11_new(NULL, 0,  0, 0, 0, 0);
        ecore_evas_title_set(ee, "TITLE");
        ecore_evas_borderless_set(ee, 0);
        ecore_evas_shaped_set(ee, 0);
        ecore_evas_show(ee);
   evas = ecore_evas_get(ee);
        evas_font_path_append(evas, "/usr/local/share/edje/data/test/fonts/");

        edje_init();
   edje = edje_object_add(evas);
        edje_object_file_set(edje, "crossfade.eet", "test");
        evas_object_move(edje, 0, 0);
        edje_object_size_min_get(edje, &amp;edje_w, &amp;edje_h);
        evas_object_resize(edje, edje_w, edje_h);
        evas_object_show(edje);

        ecore_evas_resize(ee, (int)edje_w, (int)edje_h);
        ecore_evas_show(ee);

        ecore_main_loop_begin();

        return 0;
}


int app_signal_exit(void *data, int type, void *event){

        printf("DEBUG: Exit called, shutting down\n");
        ecore_main_loop_quit();
        return 1;
}
</screen>

<para>
In this example we see Edje being initialized with edje_init(), then the edje being added to the evas similiar to any other
object being added to an evas.  The edje_object_file_set() function defines the EET to be used and the group name we wish to use
as defined in our EDC.  Using evas_object_move() we ensure that the Edje is placed in the top left corner of the evas.
Next, using edje_object_size_min_get() we return the values of the minimum width and height of the group so we can use
evas_object_resize() to resize the evas to snuggly fit our edje interface.  And finally using evas_object_show() is the usual
way we render the edje to the evas.  Following this we also resize the entire evas and re-show it to make things tidy.
Notice that the evas was created having no width or height only because we later resized it using values from the EET group.
</para>

<section>
<title>Signals and Callbacks</title>

<para>
Signals provide the communication between your interface and your application code.  When an Edje program emits a signal your
application needs to catch that signal and then do something with it, this functionality is provided by Edje signal callbacks.
The Edje API provides you with two calls, one to add and one to delete signal callbacks: edje_object_signal_callback_add() and
edje_object_signal_callback_del().  Both functions take 4 arguments: the Evas_Object (your edje), the signal thats emited,
the source of that emission, and the function that should be called when the signal is received.
These functions will not allow you to pass NULL arguments, and therefore if you want to create callbacks for several sources that
emit the same signal you will need to add a seperate callback for each of the sources.  The add function allows one more
argument, a void pointer to any data you want passed to the callback function.
</para>

<screen>
        edje_object_signal_callback_add(st_session->edje, "PLAY_PREVIOUS", "previous_button", prev_file, st_session);

        ...

void prev_file(void *user_data, Evas_Object *obj, const char *em, const char *src){
        player_session *data;

        printf("DEBUG: Previous File Called\n");        /* Report what we're doing for debugging purposes */

        data = user_data;
        ecore_idler_del(data->play_idler);      /* Stop the current playing stream */

        data->play_list = evas_list_prev(data->play_list);      /* Get the previous list item */

        if(file_is_ogg(evas_list_data(data->play_list))){       /* Make sure that the new item is really ogg */
                setup_ao();                                     /* If so, seutp the audio out path */
                get_vorbis(evas_list_data(data->play_list), data);      /* Setup the intrface with comments, etc */
                ao_open();                                      /* Open the outbound audio path */
                data->play_idler = ecore_idler_add(play_loop, data);    /* Start the play loop */
        } else {
                printf("File %s is not an OggVorbis file\n", evas_list_data(data->play_list)); /* Or, report an error */
        }
}
</screen>

<para>This is a pretty shitty example.......</para>

</section>

</chapter>

