<section>
<sectioninfo>
  <author>
    <firstname>Ben</firstname>
    <surname>Rockwood</surname>
    <email>benr@cuddletech.com</email>
    <othername>'technikolor'</othername>
  </author>
  <date>12 July 2004</date>
</sectioninfo>

<title>Recipe: Etox Overview</title>

<para>
In order to get using Etox quickly, a simple overview example is worthwhile.  In the following
example code we'll create an X11 Evas using Ecore_Evas and then put some Etox text on it.
</para>

<example>
<title>Etox Overview Example</title>
<programlisting>
#include &lt;Ecore_Evas.h&gt;
#include &lt;Ecore.h&gt;
#include &lt;Etox.h&gt;

#define WIDTH 400
#define HEIGHT 200

        Ecore_Evas  *   ee;
        Evas        *   evas;
        Evas_Object *   base_rect;
        Evas_Object *   etox;
        Etox_Context *  context;

int main(){

        ecore_init();

   ee = ecore_evas_software_x11_new(NULL, 0,  0, 0, WIDTH, HEIGHT);
        ecore_evas_title_set(ee, "ETOX Test");
        ecore_evas_borderless_set(ee, 0);
        ecore_evas_show(ee);

   evas = ecore_evas_get(ee);
        evas_font_path_append(evas, ".");

   base_rect = evas_object_rectangle_add(evas);
        evas_object_resize(base_rect, (double)WIDTH, (double)HEIGHT);
        evas_object_color_set(base_rect, 255, 255, 255, 255);
        evas_object_show(base_rect);

   etox = etox_new(evas);
        evas_object_resize(etox, WIDTH, HEIGHT);


   context = etox_get_context(etox);
        etox_context_set_color(context, 0, 0, 0, 255);
        etox_context_set_font(context, "Vera", 32);
        etox_context_set_align(context, ETOX_ALIGN_LEFT);

        etox_set_soft_wrap(etox, 1);
        etox_set_text(etox, "Welcome to the world of Etox!");

        evas_object_show(etox);

        ecore_main_loop_begin();

        return 0;
}
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
This example can be compiled in the following way:
</para>

<example>
<programlisting>
gcc `etox-config --libs --cflags` `ecore-config --libs --cflags` etox-test.c -o etox-test
</programlisting>
</example>

<para>
Most of thie example is standard Ecore_Evas functions, so we'll concentrate just on the Etox related parts of it.
Notice that we use the <function>evas_font_path_append()</function> Evas function to define our font path, this is 
something that Etox will not do for you.
</para>

<para>
Your Etox text will always start by adding a new Etox using the <function>etox_new()</function> function which returns a new
Evas_Object.  Because your Etox is itself an Evas object it can be manipulated as such.  Etox's layout functions
such as clipping and wrapping are dependant upon the size of the Etox itself, therefore <function>evas_object_resize()</function>
need to be called to define the proper size of the Etox.  Please note that the area of the object will <emphasis>not</emphasis>
default to the size of the Evas itself.  
</para>

<para>
Etox uses the concept of contexts.  A <literal>context</literal> is a set of parameters such as color, font, alignment, styles, and markers that
are applied to a certain set of text.  Each Etox object has at least one context associated with it which is created when calling
<function>etox_new()</function>.  For this reason the <function>etox_context_new()</function> function <emphasis>only</emphasis> needs
to be called when creating additional contexts. 
</para>

<para>
Once you've used <function>etox_new()</function> to add your Etox object you need to use the <function>etox_get_context()</function>
to return a <varname>Etox_Context</varname> pointer which can then be passed to other context functions to modify the attributes of your
text.  In the example we change the color, font and alignment of our context.
</para>

<para>
Two of the most interesting and simplistic features of Etox is it's ability to intellegently wrap text and to interpret a 
standard C newline charrector (\n) as a wrap.  These are features that Evas itself does not contain, it is the responsability
of the coder to ensure text doesn't trail off the canvas.  
</para>

<para>
Intellegent wrapping comes in two flavors which are not mutually exclusive.  The first is soft wrapping, which will wrap text when a charrector
is going to exceed the width of the canvas.  The second is word wrapping, which will wrap text when a word is going to exceed the width of
the canvas.  Typically  the later is desirable so that you get "This is (wrap) my string" instead of "This is m(wrap)y string."  Note, however,
that work wrapping will not work unless soft wrapping has already been turned on, thus work wrapping requires calling <emphasis>both</emphasis>
<function>etox_set_soft_wrap()</function> and <function>etox_set_word_wrap()</function> functions.
</para>

<para>
A final note about wrapping is that by default wrapping will insert a <literal>wrap marker</literal> into your output string, a "+" (plus) sign by default.
This marker indicates that a wrap has occured and is printed  as the first charrector on the next line of the wrap.  Your string will therefore
likely look more like this: "This is my (wrap) +string."  If you would prefer that Etox silently wrap without a marker, simply set the marker
to being nothing using the <function>etox_context_set_wrap_marker()</function> function.
</para>

<para>
Etox text strings themselves are set using the <function>etox_set_text()</function>.  It's important to note that the string applies to the Etox itself
and not to the context.  There is no direct association between the string and the context, which facilitates easy modification of the display of the
text without having to change the context, or vice versa.
</para>

<para>
While this is a very simple example of Etox usage, far more can be accomplished and as you can see the API is simple and clean, filling in many
of the text handling needs that Evas doesn't provide.
</para>


</section>
