<chapter>
<title>Edje Programmers Guidelines</title>

<para>
The purpose of Edje is to abstract as completely as possible the design of the interface from the application code.  Always
keep this in mind when using Edje.  While at times Edje's API seems inadequate or frustrating in its lack of customization, it
is this way for a reason: to keep you as a coder from taking power away from the themer.   If at any point the API seems like
a restriction realize that what you want to do is possible, but should be done in the EDC not in the application code.
</para>

<para>
The following recommendations are just that, recommendations.  However observing them will make your application easier to
work on and contribute to for all involved.
</para>

<section>
<title>Edje Spec Files</title>

<para>
Once you have created your application and a default EDC you will want to make it as easy as possible for other developers and
themers to create new interfaces for you application.  While developers can read your code and figure out what does what, many
of the themers can not, therefore a standardized method of describing what the application requires and provides should be utilized.
This is done by creating a flat text file named README.edje.  Below is an example of the format that should be used in your README.edje:
</para>

<figure>
<title>Example of README.edje</title>

<screen>
------------------------------------------------
EDJE Specfication
------------------------------------------------

Application: ePlayer
Author: Ben Rockwood [ benr@cuddletech.com ]
Last Update: 9/29/03
Desciption: An OggVorbis audio player


Signals accepted by application:
-------------------------------

Signal: PLAY_PREVIOUS
Source: previous_button
Desc: Signal starts playing the previous track in the playlist
                and updates track information text parts.

Signal: PLAY_NEXT
Source: next_button
Desc: Signal starts playing the next track in the playlist
                and updates track information text parts.

Signal: PLAY
Source: play_button
Desc: Signal to start playing the current track from current position,
                negates pause signal

Signal: PAUSE
Source: pause_button
Desc: Signal to pause the current playing track

Signal: SEEK_FORWARD
Source: forward_button
Desc: Signal to seek forward in track by 5 seconds

Signal: SEEK_BACK
Source: back_button
Desc: Signal to seek backwards in track by 5 seconds

Signals sent by application:
----------------------------

Signal: BLINK_ALL
Source: button
Desc: Signal signifying an error state

[ See "Signals accepted" above, application also sends these signals ]


Text parts set by application:
------------------------------

Part: title
Desc: Window title in border (ie: eVorbisPlayer v0.0)

Part: artist_name
Desc: Artist name from Ogg comments field

Part: album_name
Desc: Album name from Ogg comments field

Part: song_name
Desc: Song name from Ogg comments field

Part: time_text
Desc: Current position in track, displayed as negative
                        value to end of track (ie: -01:02)

Part: vol_display_text
Desc: Current PCM volume level, 2 digit int.  Values
                        range from 00 to 99

Swallowed areas used by application:
------------------------------------

        None.

Data fields used by application:
--------------------------------

        None.

------------------------------------------------
Features and Notes
------------------------------------------------

- Play list support currently only allows for a command line
        supplied list.
- At a bare minimum it is requested that all alternate
        pants provide Artist and Track name, Play, Next and
        Previous track.  Everything else is up to you.
- A K-Jofol look-alike interface would be kool!

------------------------------------------------
Changelog:
------------------------------------------------
9/20/03: App now will set text part "vol_display_text" to a 2 digit int
                representing PCM mixer volume level.
9/7/03: App now accepts signal PAUSE
9/5/03: Added new functions for the signals SEEK_FORWARD and SEEK_BACK
9/1/03: Initial creation.

</screen>
</figure>

<para>
This scheme allows the themer to have an understanding of what functionality is available and what
parts will be accessed by the application code and therefore must exist, even if hidden.  A changelog
should be present to list the changes in the application that could effect themes past and present.
A "Features and Notes" section is optional but allows a place to outline various functionality of the application
as well as notes from the coder to the themer as to how the app is intended to be used, their wishes, etc.
This file should be present in the top level directory of your codebase.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Source Layout</title>

<para>
Themes are typically stored in the data/ directory in the toplevel directory of your codebase.  The structure
of that directory is entirely of your own choosing.  While it is acceptable to include only a pre-compiled EET with
your code, it is highly recommended that you also include the EDC and image sources as well.  This allows users with
porting issues to rebuild the EETs themselves rather than submit needless bug reports, and for other themers to learn
from your EDC or improve upon it.  This allows themers to be more effectively leveraged to provide an even better app.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Theme  Distribution</title>

<para>
An important consideration for themeing was how to deal with distribution of themes.  Due to the ugly nature of using
renamed tarballs for data distribution Edb and then EET came to life.  EET provides a simplistic manner of distributing
complete themes and interfaces in a convenient single file package.  Because EET will compress your images there is no need
to re-compress an EET, though it is the distributers discretion to do so.  When hosting themes pre-compiled EETs should be provided.
The images and source EDC does not need to be provided, but it is recommended that you make it avalible on request or in the same place 
as the EET using a simple and clear file convension such as: theme.eet and theme-src.tgz.  Providing the source gives back to the community
not only a nice theme but also a valuable learning tool for others.  Themes should <emphasis>not</emphasis> be distributed in
tarballs as it defeats the purpose of a single file, one step distribution.
</para>
</section>

</chapter>
