<chapter>
<title>Edje Overview</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Edje is a componant of the Enlightenment Foundation Libraries which abstracts
interface design and functionality from the application code itself.   An application using
Edje is comprised of two componants, the code in the EVAS application which interacts with
the interface, and a created EET which contains all the elements of the interface itself.
These EET's are generated from an Edje EDC file in which diffrent parts of the interface
are described and laid out, and how those parts interact with your application.  This
allows for the interface to be completely changed simply by creating a new EDC and
generating the EET for your application to use.  In more popular terms, Edje
makes every application that uses it "skinable".  Raster describes Edje as "an attempt
to find a middleground between themeing and programming without turning the theme
itself into just yet another program".
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Edje Data Collections (EDC)</title>

<para>
The Edje EDC contains every detail about your interface.  An EDC is
a simple text file that uses C like syntax.  The file is broken into
three distinct sections: images, data, and collections.  The image section contains
a list of all the images your interface will use.  When you compile/generate your
EDC into an EET all the images specified will be loaded into the EET itself allowing you
to distribute your interface (or skin if you prefer) as a single file.  When
specifying your images you can even specify the ammount  you want the images to
be compressed when adding them into the EET to keep your EETs small and portable.
The collections section actually describes the interface, how it's laid out and how it
will interact with your application code. Optionally, a third section, data, can contain
arbitrary data in key-value pairs to provide data to your application.
</para>

<para>
The collections in an EDC are comprised of one or more groups.  Each group
contains parts and programs.  A part is a single element of your interface, such
as a text element, or a rectangle, or an image.  Each part is throughly described
for one or more states.  For instance, an image part might actually have two images
in it, each in a different state, one for a normal state and one for a clicked (mouse down)
state.  A part may have as many states defined as you like.
</para>

<para>
These parts are then referenced in the programs.  Programs are descriptions about
how the interface should respond to both the user and the application code itself.  A
program can accept interface events (such as mouse button 1 down), and then change the state of
a part described earlier (change to state clicked) to create an effect.  Programs
can also emit signals to your application.  In your application code you would define
a callback for that event.  Each program is concise and distinct.  For example, to
create an animated button, you would create 3 programs, one to change the image state
from normal to clicked on a mouse down event, one to emit a signal to your application on
the mouse down event, and yet another to change state back to normal on a mouse up event.
</para>

<para>
Because of the abstraction Edje provides, your applcation only needs to
know the name of the EET to use, what signals it will receive from
the interface so that callbacks can be defined when that event is received, and
what text parts in the interface can be modified.   This allows maximum flexability in
interface design, including the ability to offload the interface to graphic designers and
themers freeing the application coders, allowing users of the application to modify the
interface without hacking or forking your project, and a much quicker prototyping and design
tool than modifying your C application directly.
</para>

</section>
</chapter>
