<chapter>
<title>The Edje Preview Program</title>

<para>
The <command>edje</command> program provides an easy to use tool for previewing, testing and debugging EDCs.
The tool accepts two arguments, the first is the name of the EET to use, the second is an optional argument specifying
the Edje group to use within the EDC.  If no group name is supplied you will be presented with a list of
all the groups within the specified EET, you may click on one of the groups to preview it.
</para>

<para>
Within the <command>edje</command> source there are several printf() statements, which by default are commented out.
Uncommenting these statements will cause the tool to print to STDOUT all events, signals and program starts and stops
which is useful in debugging.  If you choose to use <command>edje</command> for debugging purposes it is highly recommended
you enable this output.  You can find the source for the <command>edje</command> program in <filename>edje/src/bin/edje_main.c</filename>.
</para>

<para>
It should be noted that the <command>edje</command> tool does not automatically resize to fit your interface as defined by
min and max size for the group.  The default window size is 240x320.  In order to see your interface at the proper default size
you should resize the preview window (the window inside your window managers window) larger and then resize it down till it stops
on the minimum size of the interface.  [ NOTE: Hopefully this will be fixed in time. ]
</para>

<para>
Because certain elements of Edje need to be specified in code, <command>edje</command> provides you with some code side elements you
can draw on for design and debugging purposes.  It defines the EVAS font path to two locations: <filename>(data_dir)/data/test/fonts</filename>
(typical <filename>/usr/local/share/</filename>) and <filename>./fonts/</filename>.  Therefore when using <command>edje</command>
for debugging you should include all your custom fonts in a <filename>fonts/</filename> directory relative to where you preview it from.
Several key events are accepted for testing purposes.  edje_object_play_set(edje, 1) is executed when the RETURN key is pressed, and
edje_object_play_set(edje, 0) is executed when ESC is pressed.  edje_object_animation_set(edje, 1) is executed when key A is pressed,
and edje_object_animation_set(edje, 0) when key S is pressed.  Using the directional keys UP, LEFT and RIGHT will change the text string
of a text part named "text" to "String 1" for LEFT, "Buttox" for UP, and "You presed (KEY).." for RIGHT.  Further, four color classes
are defined, each with the color class name "bg", using the F1, F2, F3 and F4 keys.
</para>

<table><title>Edje Tool Event Facilities</title>
<tgroup cols='2' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
<colspec align='right'/>
<colspec align='left'/>
<thead>
<row>
  <entry>Key Press</entry>
  <entry>Edje Function Called</entry>
</row>
</thead>

<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>RETURN
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_play_set(edje, 1);
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>ESC
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_play_set(edje, 0);
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>a
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_animation_set(edje, 1);
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>s
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_animation_set(edje, 0);
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>LEFT_ARROW
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_part_text_set(edje, "text", "String 1");
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>UP_ARROW
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_part_text_set(edje, "text", "Buttox");
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>RIGHT_ARROW
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_part_text_set(edje, "text", "You pressed \"U\". Nice one stenchie!");
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>F1
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_color_class_set(edje, "bg",
                                           255, 255, 255, 255,
                                           0, 0, 0, 0,
                                           0, 0, 0, 0);
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>F2
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_color_class_set(edje, "bg",
                                           255, 200, 120, 255,
                                           0, 0, 0, 0,
                                           0, 0, 0, 0);
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>F3
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_color_class_set(edje, "bg",
                                           120, 200, 255, 200,
                                           0, 0, 0, 0,
                                           0, 0, 0, 0);
        </entry>
</row>

<row>
  <entry>F4
        </entry>
  <entry>edje_object_color_class_set(edje, "bg",
                                           255, 200, 50, 100,
                                           0, 0, 0, 0,
                                           0, 0, 0, 0);
        </entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<para>
Effective use of the <command>edje</command> tool can significantly ease debugging of your Edje interface.
</para>

</chapter>
