<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  -->

<refentry id='e16.man'>
 <refentryinfo>
  <productname>e16</productname>
  <!--pubdate>__date__</pubdate-->
  <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <firstname>The Enlightenment Team</firstname>
    <contrib/>
    <email>enlightenment-devel@lists.sourceforge.net</email>
   </author>
   <author>
    <firstname>Kim</firstname><surname>Woelders</surname>
    <contrib/>
    <email>kim@woelders.dk</email>
   </author>
  </authorgroup>
 </refentryinfo>

 <refmeta>
  <refentrytitle>e16</refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
  <refmiscinfo class='date'>__date__</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo class='source'>e16 __version__</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo class='manual'>e16 documentation</refmiscinfo>
 </refmeta>

 <refnamediv id='name'>
  <refname>e16</refname>
  <refpurpose>The Enlightenment DR16 Window Manager</refpurpose>
 </refnamediv>

 <!-- body begins here -->

<refsect1 id='documentation'><title>e16 documentation</title>

<refsect2 id='front'><title><markup role="dox-center"/>Enlightenment version 0.16.8</title>
<img src="E_logo.png" x="32" y="77"/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para><markup role="dox-center"/>
Topics:
</para>
<para><markup role="dox-center"/><simplelist>
<member><link linkend="aboutdox">How To Use Documentation</link></member>
<member><link linkend="about">About Enlightenment</link></member>
<member><link linkend="res">Resources</link></member>
<member></member>
<member><link linkend="docindex">User Documentation</link></member>
<member><link linkend="faq">Frequently Asked Questions</link></member>
</simplelist></para>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<font face="Vera/10" color="#ffffff"/>
<para>
Welcome to the Enlightenment Documentation Viewer.  Please select a topic from
the list.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id='aboutdox'><title/>
<para>
This Documentation is intended to take you step by step through Enlightenment(E16)
and its default setup, how to use it, modify settings, and put it to use for
you. When you have finished reading each page please press the NEXT button to go
to the next page, or use the Back button until you have reached the
<link linkend="docindex">Docs Index</link>.
</para>
<para>
If you are reading this right now you have managed to get E16 itself
installed correctly and are either running E16 for the first time or
have just upgraded to a new version. Congratulations. Now it's time to take
you on a quick tour of the desktop you will have before you.
</para>
<para>
Please remember that if you use a <link linkend="themes">theme</link> other than
Brushed Metal that it may look slightly or completely different to the
contents of this User Documentation. Some behavior may also vary.
</para>
<para>
To relaunch this Help Browser at any time, middle click on your
<link linkend="desktops">desktop</link> and select the "Help" Item.  The documentation should come
back up, reloading to the first page.
You can also use the "Home" key to take you back to the introduction page at
any time during the program.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="about"><title></title>
<para>
E16 is your Window Manager. The Window Manager controls the
appearance of the borders of your windows, their behavior and
all user interaction with positioning, killing, resizing, moving, iconifying,
shading etc. your windows, virtual desktops, multiple desktops, menus attached
to windows and some root window menus and can also control the background
of your desktop(s).
</para>
<para>
E16 is a large and complex program and is by no means perfect,
but it is being worked on and is as stable as possible. It has many advanced
features, but may also be missing some features that you would like to see.
The version you are now running (0.16.8) is by no means the
end of development and improvements, fixes and new exciting features are
being worked on all the time. Please visit the <link linkend="res">Web</link> site often for
new versions, fixes, patches and updates.
</para>
<para>
We hope that you enjoy using E16 as much as we have enjoyed writing
it.  We'd like to think that even if this isn't the right software for you, you
at least can have fun playing around with what we have created.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="res"><title>Resources</title>
<para>
Web site: http://www.enlightenment.org/
</para>
<para>
Forums: http://forum.enlightenment.org/
</para>
<para>
Bugs: http://bugs.enlightenment.org/
</para>
<para/>
<para>
Download: http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=2
</para>
<para>
Mailing lists: http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=2
</para>
<para>
IRC: #E on freenode
</para>
</refsect2>


<!-- should have columns=2 -->
<refsect2 id="docindex"><title>Documentation Index</title>
<para><simplelist>
<member><link linkend="basicintro">Basic Intro</link></member>
<member><link linkend="rootmenu">Using Menus</link></member>
<member><link linkend="mousebind">Mouse Bindings</link></member>
<member><link linkend="mouseconfig">Mouse Configuration</link></member>
<member><link linkend="border">Using The Window Border</link></member>
<member><link linkend="changeborder">Changing Window Borders</link></member>
<member><link linkend="defkeys">Default Keybindings</link></member>
<member><link linkend="desktops">Multiple Desktops</link></member>
<member><link linkend="changedesk">Changing Desktops</link></member>
<member><link linkend="appsdesk">Taking Apps Between Desks</link></member>
<member><link linkend="dragbar">The Dragbar</link></member>
<member><link linkend="pager">The Pager</link></member>
<member><link linkend="iconbox">The Iconbox</link></member>
<member><link linkend="minimized">Recovering Minimized Apps</link></member>
<member><link linkend="properties">Remembering App Properties</link></member>
<member><link linkend="settings">Intro To Settings</link></member>
<member><link linkend="groups">Window Groups</link></member>
</simplelist></para>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para><simplelist>
<member><link linkend="backgrounds">Desktop Backgrounds</link></member>
<member><link linkend="tooltips">Tooltips</link></member>
<member><link linkend="audio">Audio</link></member>
<member><link linkend="fx">Special Effects</link></member>
<member><link linkend="focus">Setting The Focus</link></member>
<member><link linkend="movemode">Moving Windows</link></member>
<member><link linkend="resizemode">Resizing Windows</link></member>
<member><link linkend="windowops">Window Operations</link></member>
<member><link linkend="placement">Window Placement Options</link></member>
<member><link linkend="placement">Autoraise Settings</link></member>
<member><link linkend="eesh">Quick Intro to IPC</link></member>
<member><link linkend="editmenus">How To Edit Menus</link></member>
<member><link linkend="editkeys">How To Change Keybindings</link></member>
<member><link linkend="themes">Themes</link></member>
<member><link linkend="eyecandy">Extra Eyecandy</link></member>
<member><link linkend="maint">Maintenance Scripts</link></member>
</simplelist></para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="basicintro"><title/>
<img src="E_screen_start.png" x="16" y="16"/>
<para>
Now that you have started E16, if you are using it for your desktop
shell, your screen should look something like the image here on the left.
</para>
<para>
Across the whole top of the screen you will see a bar with arrows pointing
up and down on the left and right ends. This is your desktop
<link linkend="dragbar">Dragbar</link>.
</para>
<para>
On the bottom-left you'll see 3 boxes. The top box with the scrollbar attached
will be your <link linkend="iconbox">Iconbox</link>.
</para>
<para>
The other 2 boxes below it are <link linkend="pager">Pagers</link> for desktops 0 and 1. Everything
else is your desktop background.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="rootmenu"><title>Using Menus</title>
<img src="E_app_menu.png" x="350" y="38"/>
<para>
When you click with your left mouse button on the desktop <link linkend="backgrounds">background</link> you will
see an "User Menus" menu appear (example displayed on the right here).
Applications you may have installed will appear in this menu. To launch one
of them simply select it from the menu.
</para>
<para>
Note: Menus in E16 work like most menu systems. Either hold
down the mouse button and navigate with the button down, releasing on the
selection you want, or release elsewhere to not select anything. You can also
quickly click and release, then navigate: move the mouse, and click
again on the item you wish to select, or elsewhere if you do not wish to
select an entry.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="tut4"><title/>
<img src="E_settings_menu.png" x="285" y="235"/>
<img src="E_enlightenment_menu.png" x="4" y="30"/>
<para/>
<para>
Clicking the middle button on the desktop <link linkend="backgrounds">background</link> will display
E16's main menu. You can access the other menus plus more options
from this menu (including those to log out, restart and display Help
information). A sample of this menu is shown to our left.
</para>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para>
When you click the right mouse button
a menu with the title "Settings" will appear. This is
E16's <link linkend="settings">settings</link> menu. From it you can select various
configuration dialogs that will assist you in customizing your desktop to
better suit your needs.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="mousebind"><title>Mouse Bindings</title>
<para>
Of course, when you click on the <link linkend="desktops">desktop</link> <link linkend="backgrounds">background</link> of
your screen, normally you will bring up a <link linkend="rootmenu">menu</link>.  And of course, when you
click on the <link linkend="border">border</link> of a window, you will do various things.  But these
are not the only things you can do with your mouse.
</para>
<para>
In E16, there are several other actions that the mouse can do by
default.  For example, by holding down the ALT key when you click the left
mouse button anywhere in a window, you will find that you can <link linkend="movemode">move</link> the window
around the screen, just as if you had used the titlebar.  You can also ALT
middle-click in a window to <link linkend="resizemode">resize</link> it, or use ALT and right-click to bring up
the <link linkend="windowops">Window Operations Menu</link>.
</para>
<para>
You will find that holding down the ALT key while clicking the middle
mouse button on the background of your <link linkend="desktops">desktop</link> will bring up a
menu with the titles of all currently active
application windows. Selecting one of these will take you to that application.
By using the CTRL key instead of ALT you will get a menu displaying all
current desktops as sub-menus, with applications on each desktop in the
desktop sub-menu.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="mouseconfig"><title>Mouse Configuration</title>
<para>
E16 makes extensive use of the mouse.
However, you may be missing some features because of the way
that your mouse is configured on your X server.
</para>
<para>
If your mouse does not have a middle button you should enable
"Emulate 3 Buttons" in your X server. This option allows you to
emulate a three-button mouse by pressing both left and
right mouse buttons at once.
If this does not work, three-button emulation  may not be enabled. See
your X server documentation to configure this emulation.
</para>
<para>
This may vary from system to system. The OS and X server may also
vary the method in which you do this, if it is possible. Not having
a middle mouse button in
E16, or for that matter X, is not a good thing as it is almost
assumed to be there, and is used by many applications, including E.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="tut6"><title/>
<img src="E_mousewheel.png" x="370" y="30"/>
<img src="E_mouse.png" x="410" y="330"/>
<para>
If you have a Wheel-Mouse and X is configured to use it, E16
supports it by default.
</para>
<para>
Rolling your wheel up on the desktop background will take you back a
<link linkend="desktops">desktop</link>. Rolling your wheel downward you will advance
forward a desktop.
</para>
<para>
If this doesn't work, then it may be you haven't configured your X server to
understand a mouse with a wheel. You may need to edit your X server
configuration to have a "Pointer" Section like:
</para>
<font face="Vera/11" color="#ccaacc"/>
<para><simplelist>
<member>Section "Pointer"</member>
<member>Protocol    "MousemanPlusPS/2"</member>
<member>Device      "/dev/mouse"</member>
<member>ZAxisMapping 4 5</member>
<member>Buttons      5</member>
<member>EndSection</member>
</simplelist></para>
<font face="Vera/11" color="#ffffff"/>
<para>
You may need to modify this for your mouse.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="border"><title>Using the Window Border</title>
<para>
When you start an application, unless it has special properties, it will come
up on your screen with a border surrounding it that contains a titlebar and
several control buttons.
This border is the primary interface to controlling an application window.
The Default setup (shown on the next page) gives adequate control but still
retains simplicity.
</para>
<para>
If you click left mouse button on the titlebar and keep the mouse button down
the window will follow your mouse wherever it moves. Respectively if you click
your left mouse button and drag on any of the resize handles, the window will
be resized in that direction. Clicking right mouse button on the resize
handles will raise the windows to the top.
</para>
<para>
Clicking right mouse button on the titlebar or any button on the window
operations menu button on the top-left will display a menu that has window
manipulation options in it.
</para>
<para>
Double-Clicking the title bar will make the Window shade or unshade.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="tut8"><title/>
<img src="E_window_diagram.png" x="16" y="48"/>
<para/>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="tut9"><title/>
<para>
Clicking left mouse button on the iconify button will iconify the window
and send it off to the <link linkend="iconbox">Iconbox</link>. Hitting the Maximize button will
maximize the
size of the application fill your screen. Hitting it again will Unmaximize,
bringing the window back to its normal size.
</para>
<para>
Clicking with the left mouse button on the close button will close the window.
If the application that owns that window does not respond to a nice request to
exit, then press the right mouse button on the close button to forcibly
terminate that window. This should not be used unless the application is
visibly "hung".
</para>
<para>
In addition to these methods, there are additional ways to manipulation
windows.
</para>
<para>
If you hold down the ALT key and hold down left mouse button anywhere in the
window (on the border OR in the application part) while dragging, you will
move this window around. Doing the same but with the middle mouse button will
resize the window in that direction. Clicking the right mouse button anywhere
in the window while holding down the ALT key will bring up the window
operations menu.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="changeborder"><title>Changing Window Borders</title>
<img src="E_border_selector.png" x="300" y="40"/>
<para>
You may find that you don't like a particular border that a
window uses, for some reason or another.  You can easily change the border
style of a window in E16 using the <link linkend="windowops">Window Operations</link>
menu, however.  Select the "Set Border Style" menu, and a list will be
presented to you of available borders in this theme.  The most common use
for this is to make an application shed its border, using the
BORDERLESS border type.
</para>
<para>
You can always click with ALT + Right mouse button anywhere in the window to
bring up the window operations menu again.
</para>
<para>
If you want to remember the border style for the next time you run this
application, you can always use the <link linkend="properties">Remember</link> dialog to remember
the current window border.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="defkeys"><title>Default Keybindings</title>
<img src="E_keyboard.png" x="312" y="0"/>
<para>
Below are the keybindings for E as it comes "from the factory"
</para>
<font face="Vera/10" color="#112222"/>
<para><simplelist>
<member>CTRL+ALT+Home - Re-shuffle windows on screen to be Clean</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+Del - Exit E16 and Log Out</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+End - Restart E16</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+Up-Arrow - Raise window to top</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+Down-Arrow - Lower window to the bottom</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+Left-Arrow - Go to the previous desktop</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+Right-Arrow - Go to the next desktop</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+X - Close the currently focused window</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+K - Kill the currently focused window nastily</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+I - Iconify the currently focused window</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+R - Shade/Unshade the currently focused window</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+S - Stick/Unstick the currently focused window</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+M - Maximize/unmaximize the currently focused window</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+F - Toggle fullscreen mode of the currently focused window</member>
<member>CTRL+ALT+(F1 - F8) - Go directly to desktops 0 - 7</member>
</simplelist></para>
<font face="Vera/11" color="#ffffff"/>
<para>
(more on next page ...)
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="tut11"><title/>
<font face="Vera/10" color="#112222"/>
<para><simplelist>
<member>ALT+Tab - Switch focus to the next window</member>
<member>ALT+Enter - Zoom/Unzoom the currently focused window</member>
<member>SHIFT+ALT+Left-Arrow - Move to the virtual desktop on the left</member>
<member>SHIFT+ALT+Right-Arrow - Move to the virtual desktop on the right</member>
<member>SHIFT+ALT+Up-Arrow - Move to the virtual desktop above</member>
<member>SHIFT+ALT+Down-Arrow - Move to the virtual desktop below</member>
</simplelist></para>
<font face="Vera/11" color="#ffffff"/>
<para>
Note: Zooming in and out of windows will only work if you have an X server
that implements the Xf86VidMode extension. You also need to define multiple
screen modes for your display, e.g. with a "Display" subsection of the X11
configuration that looks like:
</para>
<font face="Vera/11" color="#ccaacc"/>
<para><simplelist>
<member>SubSection "Display"</member>
<member>	Depth 16</member>
<member>	Modes "1600x1200" "1280x1024" "1152x864" "1024x768" "800x600" "640x480" "512x384" "400x300" "320x240"</member>
<member>EndSubSection</member>
</simplelist></para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="desktops"><title>Multiple &amp; Virtual Desktops</title>
<img src="E_deskstack.png" x="360" y="70"/>
<para>
E16 supports both Multiple and Virtual desktops. There are
distinct difference between the two, and E16 treats them differently.
</para>
<para>
When you start E16 you will by default have two desktops. In
E16 desktops are geometrically unrelated work areas. They are
visually stacked on top of each other and can even be dragged down to expose
desktops underneath.
</para>
<para>
The best way to imagine this is that each desktop is a sheet of paper with the
first desktop (desktop 0) being glued in-place. You can re-shuffle the stack
of papers and slide one down to reveal a piece of paper underneath - the only
paper you can't slide is the first one. Each desktop (or sheet) contains your
application windows.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="desktops2"><title/>
<img src="E_deskarray.png" x="350" y="140"/>
<para>
Windows normally live on one desktop, but can be made
to exist on all desktops - whenever you change to a new desktop the window
will follow you and be on that desktop too. This is known as being sticky.
if a window is sticky it will "stick to the glass of your screen" and stay
there until it is not sticky anymore or the window is closed.
</para>
<para>
Virtual desktops (also known as desktop areas) is a measure of how big your
desktops are. A desktop can be a multiple of your screen size in size (2x1,
2x2, 3x3, 4x2 etc.). That means each desktop has an AxB screen size of area
allocated to it and you can be looking at any screen-sized part of it at any
time. It's just like getting more sheets of paper and taping them to the sides
of your current sheet of paper. An easy way of changing your view is by just
sliding your mouse in the direction of a currently unviewable part of your
desktop. As long as you have Edge Flip enabled E16 will
automatically scroll over to that part of the desktop.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="desktops3"><title/>
<img src="E_virtual_desk_settings.png" x="335" y="51"/>
<img src="E_area_settings.png" x="30" y="190"/>
<para>
To change the number of virtual desktops that you have, use the "Multiple
Desktop Settings" dialog from the right mouse <link linkend="settings">Settings Menu</link>.  You
should see a menu that looks something like the menu to the right.  You can use
the slider bar to quickly select the appropriate number of virtual desktops you
would like to use.
</para>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para>
To change the number of virtual areas, use the "Virtual Desktop Settings"
menu.  This will bring up a menu that looks something like the one on the left.
Use the slider bars to extend the size of the virtual areas to the size that
you prefer. You can also use this dialog to enable/disable edge
resistance (when your <link linkend="mousebind">mouse</link> hits the edge of an area) moving between
virtual areas.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="desktops4"><title/>
<img src="E_deskimg.png" x="275" y="81"/>
<para>
E16 also allows you to set a different desktop backdrop per desktop
to help you customize your environment and differentiate which desktop is
which.
</para>
<para>
An easy way of having E16 automatically pick up any pictures you have
is to make a directory in your ~/.e16 directory called
backgrounds and then fill that with your favorite backdrops. E16
will automatically discover this and index them for you allowing you to
select them and change their settings. More on this topic is explained in the
<link linkend="backgrounds">Desktop Backgrounds</link> section.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="changedesk"><title>Changing Desktops</title>
<para>
There are several ways that you can change your current desktop - let's go over
a few of them here.
</para>
<para><simplelist>
<member>You can use the <link linkend="defkeys">Keybindings</link> alt-F1 through alt-F8 for the first 8
desktops.</member>
<member>You can use the <link linkend="defkeys">Keybindings</link> Ctrl-Alt-Left and Ctrl-Alt-Right to
navigate to the next/previous desktop.</member>
<member>You can use the <link linkend="tut11">Keybindings</link> shift-alt-directional arrow to change
virtual areas in a given direction.</member>
<member>You can use the <link linkend="pager">Pager</link> to quickly navigate to the desktop/area you want
by clicking on the desired area.</member>
<member>You can use the <link linkend="dragbar">Dragbar</link> to quickly navigate to a particular
application or a particular desktop by using the middle and right mouse
buttons.</member>
<member>You can also use external applications such as the GNOME panel's pager or the
KDE panel's pager to navigate desktops and/or applications.</member>
</simplelist></para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="appsdesk"><title>Moving Applications Between Desktops</title>
<para>
There are several ways that you can move applications from one desktop to
another.  We'll go over a few of them now.
</para>
<para>
The first way you can move apps between desktops is using the <link linkend="pager">Pager</link>.
</para>
<para>
You can also move applications between desktops using the <link linkend="dragbar">Dragbar</link>.
</para>
<para>
You can also move applications between desktops using the KDE or GNOME
desktop pagers.
</para>
<para>
You can also <link linkend="movemode">move</link> a window, then bring the window with you as you
change desktops using <link linkend="defkeys">keybinding</link>.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="dragbar"><title>The Dragbar</title>
<img src="E_dragbar.png" x="10" y="345"/>
<img src="E_dragging_desktops.png" x="315" y="20"/>
<para>
If you look along the top of your screen, you will notice a long thin bar that
looks something like the bar pictured below.  This is called your Dragbar.  It
gets its name from its primary purpose, which is dragging desktops around.
</para>
<para>
If you are on any desktop except desktop 0, you can pick up and move that desktop
in another direction.  <link linkend="desktops">Desktops</link> documentation has more information
on how to change desktops.  Once you have dragged a desktop down, you can
proceed to move windows between desktops this way, instead of using the
<link linkend="pager">pager</link>.
</para>
<para>
You can also use the Dragbar to retrieve windowlists.  Use the middle mouse
button to retrieve a windowlist, and the right mouse button for a
windowlist sorted by desktops.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="pager"><title>The Pager</title>
<img src="E_pager.png" x="320" y="70"/>
<para>
Pagers may not be a new idea in desktop environments, but the Pager in
E16 (as seen on the right) is a highly advanced and highly
configurable tool for desktop and window control, as well as a navigation tool.
</para>
<para>
The pager lets you see your desktop screen area in miniature. It lets you click
on a certain desktop to "visit" it, click and drag windows around in the pager
itself to move them about the screen quickly, or between <link linkend="desktops">desktops</link>.
In this example, we have two virtual areas.  You can see the current area (the
one with the windows in it) is also highlighted.
</para>
<para>
Dragging a window from
one area of a pager to another will move it there, or to another desktop.
Dragging it out onto the actual desktop will drop that window right there.
You can also drag a window into the <link linkend="iconbox">Iconbox</link> to iconify the window.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="pager2"><title/>
<img src="E_pager_settings_menu.png" x="8" y="30"/>
<img src="E_pager_settings.png" x="208" y="180"/>
<para>
Pressing right-mouse button over a blank portion of the pager gets you the
pager menu, allowing you to change settings.  This will allow you to
set a couple of quick options, as shown on the left.  For more available
options, you can select the "Pager Settings" item, and another dialog will pop
up, that looks like the one below.
</para>
<para>
This dialog box will allow you to set all sorts of additional parameters, many
of which can increase the performance of E16 on your system.
Disabling high quality snapshots and/or snapshots in general as well as
continuous updates can seriously improve performance - these features are
intended for high end machines.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="pager3"><title/>
<img src="E_pager.png" x="340" y="140"/>
<para>
You can resize the pager to make it the size you'd like.  Hold down
ALT and use the middle-mouse button to resize the pager in any direction. Using
left-mouse button while holding ALT and dragging will move the window. Holding
down ALT while pressing right-mouse button, just like any normal window will
get you a window operations menu.
</para>
<para>
In the default theme clicking the tab on the right side of the pager with the
arrow pointing right will shade and unshade the pager window horizontally,
allowing you to hide and unhide the window easily.
</para>
<para>
The striped area above this tab on the pager's border is a handle that will
allow you to move the pager about, just like the titlebar of any window.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="iconbox"><title>The Iconbox</title>
<img src="E_iconbox.png" x="300" y="90"/>
<para>
The iconbox is the place the icons for all your iconified windows go.  It is
one method of recovering <link linkend="minimized">minimized</link> applications.  Whenever
you iconify or minimize a window it will go into an iconbox and have an icon
displayed for it there. Clicking on the icon again will de-iconify it.
</para>
<para>
You can have as many icon boxes on your desktop as you want to.  You can create
more by using the Middle Click <link linkend="rootmenu">Menu</link> - select Desktop->Create New Iconbox
and a new Iconbox will pop up on your desktop.  Each of these Iconboxes can
have individual configurations, as detailed on the next page.
</para>
<para>
You can <link linkend="movemode">move</link> the Iconbox around the screen using Alt-Leftclick
on the window, and then moving it to the desired location on the screen.  You
can <link linkend="resizemode">resize</link> the Iconbox by alt-middleclicking on the window and
then adjusting the size  as described in the <link linkend="mousebind">Mouse Bindings</link>
section.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="iconbox2"><title/>
<img src="E_iconbox_menu.png" x="300" y="20"/>
<img src="E_iconbox_settings.png" x="10" y="200"/>
<para>
Clicking the right-mouse button anywhere in the Iconbox will bring up a menu
to configure that iconbox.  This menu will look a little something like the one
here to the right.  This menu allows you to also close the Iconbox or open up
an additional Iconbox.
</para>
<para>
To change the settings of an individual Iconbox, we'll use the right mouse
button <link linkend="mousebind">menu</link> and select "This
Iconbox Settings" - this should get us a dialog that looks something like the
one  to our left.  You can change the orientation, icon size, scrollbar
options, display policy, base image, and many more options of the Iconbox
from this dialog.  You may choose to change the anchor of
alignment for resizes - play with it until it resizes appropriately for your
Iconbox location.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="iconbox3"><title/>
<para>
If you want to customize the images used for the icons in your iconbox, there
is already an example configuration supplied. To make your own configuration
copy the matches.cfg file installed in your E16 system config
directory (/usr/local/e16/config/matches.cfg or
/usr/share/e16/config/matches.cfg) to your ~/.e16 directory and then edit it.
</para>
<para>
There are several examples of using the globbing and matching in the system
matches.cfg file. Use that as a reference for your own additions.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="minimized"><title>Recovering Minimized Applications</title>
<para>
There are several ways to recover an application once you have minimized it.
The most obvious way is to use the <link linkend="iconbox">Iconbox</link>.  Of course, you might
have had some applications in your Iconbox when you accidentally closed it.  Or
maybe you minimized some applications and forgot you didn't have an Iconbox.
Or maybe you don't like the Iconbox and usually use KDE or GNOME's panel to
recover them and forgot to launch them.  Never fear.  You can always
middle click on the <link linkend="dragbar">Dragbar</link>
and get a <link linkend="rootmenu">menu</link> that will allow you
to recover them.  You can also Alt or Ctrl-Middleclick on the desktop to get
the same menus (in case you don't have a Dragbar anymore).
</para>
<para>
Remember, at any time you can always create a new <link linkend="iconbox">Iconbox</link> to catch
your applications as they minimize, if you want to re-enable it.  Unfortunately
you'll have to reconfigure it since each Iconbox can have its own
<link linkend="settings">settings</link>.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="properties"><title>Remembering Application Properties</title>
<img src="E_remember_settings.png" x="320" y="50"/>
<para>
In the <link linkend="windowops">Window Operations</link> menu of every window you will see an
entry labeled
"Remember...". If you select this it will bring up the "Remember" dialog for
that window, as shown to our right.
</para>
<para>
This dialog lets you selectively snapshot certain attributes of that window at
that time and have E16 remember them. You may choose to only remember
some of the attributes, and possibly not have the application started
automatically for you. Choose what you want E16 to remember about that
window and hit "Apply" or "OK" if you don't need the dialog anymore, and
E16 will, the next time that instance of the application is run,
apply the current location, size, border style or any other attribute to
that window. E16 can also launch the application for you upon startup
if you so wish.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="settings"><title>Settings</title>
<img src="E_settings_menu.png" x="240" y="87"/>
<para>
When you click the right mouse button on the desktop background you will pop
up the Settings menu. From here you can select an aspect of E16 to
configure to your liking. There are too many settings to actually document
fully right now, but the likelihood is if you want a particular behavior from
E16, it is achievable by merely playing with these options.
</para>
<para>
Combinations of options are often required to get the effect you want, so some
experimentation may be required. Do not be frightened. Nothing you can do
can't be undone by simply changing the options back to how they were and
clicking on Apply again.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="groups"><title>Window Groups</title>
<img src="E_group_settings.png" x="370" y="255"/>
<para>
Sometimes you have a number of windows on your desktop that logically go
together. E16 allows you to group windows
together, so that whenever you change a property of one window in a group,
the change is reflected on the other group members. If you have a group whose
members span multiple <link linkend="desktops">desktops</link>, changing a group's property
affects only windows of that group that are on the current desktop.
</para>
<para>
The properties that you can change for an entire group include setting the window
border, iconifying, killing, moving, raising/lowering, sticking and shading of
a window.
</para>
<para>
To define what properties are applied to a group by default, you go to the
<link linkend="settings">settings</link> menu and pick the "Group Settings" option, which will give
you a dialog window in which you can configure the settings, as shown here on
the right.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="groups2"><title/>
<img src="E_groups_menu.png" x="320" y="25"/>
<para>
There are two different methods for manipulating window groups. First, there's a
comprehensive submenu available in each window's operations menu
called "Window Groups".  This menu is shown here on the right.  You also are
able to configure the group individually apart from the default group settings
(as shown on the previous page).
</para>
<para>
The second way is the window titlebar, which has the most important options
directly available for convenience. Shift-click to start a group,
Ctrl-clicking to add a window to the youngest group (also referred to as the
"current" group) and Shift-Ctrl-Click to destroying a group. You can also click
the middle mouse button for visualizing the group(s) of a window. Click again
to returning to the previous border.
</para>
<para>
Windows can be in multiple groups at the same time, so for many
options you have to indicate which group you are referring to.
Selecting the appropriate checkboxes (showing the group members' titles)
at the top of the dialog windows.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="backgrounds"><title>Selecting and Adding backgrounds</title>
<para>
Often you will want to change the background of a particular desktop.  There
are several ways you can do this.  But of course, to change your desktop,
you'll need to give E16 some graphics to play with.  A desktop
theme may add a background or two to your available selections, but
most users want to have even more backgrounds to choose from.
To add backgrounds to your selection, make a backgrounds directory under your
home directory.  To do this using most shells you can type
</para>
<para>
mkdir ~/.e16/backgrounds
</para>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para>
(more on next page ...)
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="backgrounds2"><title/>
<img src="E_backgrounds_menu.png" x="163" y="70"/>
<para>
Once you have added your backgrounds, you should be
able to go to the root menu desktop selector.  To get to this menu, middle
click on the desktop, select "Desktop",
and go to Backgrounds.  You should get something that looks similar to the
image  on the right.  From here you will be able to navigate the backgrounds
menus.
</para>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para>
(more on next page ...)
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="backgrounds3"><title/>
<img src="E_backgrounds_menu_view.png" x="3" y="84"/>
<para>
Once you have opened up the backgrounds menu, you should see something similar
to the image below.  From here, you can put your mouse over any of the images
there, and it will change the desktop background of the current desktop to the
image that you have selected.
</para>
<para>
E16 will attempt to choose the best
settings for a particular background, but if it gets it wrong you can always
change the settings by hand.  By bringing up the settings menu with the right
mouse button and selecting the "Desktop Background Settings" item, you can
bring up a dialog that looks something like the one on the next page ...
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="backgrounds4"><title/>
<img src="E_backgrounds_settings.png" x="0" y="0"/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para>
You can use this dialog to change your background, too, as well as fine-tune
all the various settings for each individual background available.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="tooltips"><title>Tooltips</title>
<img src="E_tooltips.png" x="260" y="65"/>
<img src="E_tooltip_settings.png" x="20" y="245"/>
<para>
From time to time, as you use E16, if you don't remember what does
what, if you keep the mouse still for a little bit a tooltip will pop up.  The
easiest example of this is when you hold the mouse over a <link linkend="border">Window Border</link>.
</para>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para>
You can disable the tooltips or change the delay before they pop up by
selecting the "Tooltip Settings" dialog from the <link linkend="settings">settings</link> menu, as
shown here on the left.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="audio"><title>Audio</title>
<img src="E_audio_settings.png" x="300" y="180"/>
<para>
Of course, E16 comes preconfigured to play lots of little blips and
beeps when you do various things on your desktop.  In order to use sound in
E16, you must have both EsounD and audiofile installed.
</para>
<para/>
<para/>
<para/>
<para>
You can enable and/or disable sound at runtime simply by selecting from the
<link linkend="settings">Settings</link> menu the "Audio Settings" option, which brings up a dialog,
shown here at right.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="fx"><title>Special Effects</title>
<img src="E_special_fx_settings.png" x="320" y="60"/>
<para>
E16 has many features that are configured via the "Special FX"
<link linkend="settings">Settings</link> dialog.  Here you can configure the <link linkend="dragbar">Dragbar</link>,
various sliding speeds (including the speed of a windowshade), as well as
toggle animation of different features.  You can also configure the method used
for sliding windows, similar to <link linkend="resizemode">Resize Modes</link>.
</para>
<para>
There are several FX features disabled by default
in a new installation, including the animated display of menus.  You can also
enable saveunders here, which may improve or slow down the performance of
E16 on your X server, depending on server and configuration.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="focus"><title>Setting the Focus</title>
<img src="E_mouse.png" x="410" y="330"/>
<para>
E16 offers lots of different options for focusing windows.  By
default, it comes up in sloppy focus mode.  There are two other primary focus
modes supported by E16 - click to focus and pointer focus.
</para>
<para>
Click To Focus most people are familiar with.  You click on a window and it
receives the focus from E16.
</para>
<para>
Pointer Focus gives the focus to whichever window the pointer is sitting over
</para>
<para>
Sloppy Focus is similar to Pointer Focus, except that if you go over the
<link linkend="backgrounds">Desktop Background</link> you still are focused on the last window
</para>
<para>
Next we'll tell you how to change these settings.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="focus2"><title/>
<img src="E_focus_settings.png" x="320" y="20"/>
<para>
E16 allows you to change your focus settings at any time.  Simply
bring up the <link linkend="settings">Settings</link> menu and then select "Focus Settings" to bring
up a dialog that looks something like the one on the right.  At the top, we can
select between our three focus modes, as described on the previous page.
</para>
<para>
We can also enable some other features, such as one that will allow a simple
<link linkend="mousebind">mouse</link> click to raise any window to the foreground, as well as several
other advanced focus settings.
</para>
<para>
Here we can also enable the focuslist feature.  The focuslist is a window list
that pops up as you cycle through your focus using the ALT + TAB
<link linkend="defkeys">Keybinding</link>.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="movemode"><title>Moving Windows</title>
<img src="E_move_resize_settings.png" x="300" y="50"/>
<para>
E16 comes with several different available methods for moving a
window.  You can perform the actual moves using the Window <link linkend="border">Border</link>,
or by using the available <link linkend="mousebind">Mouse Bindings</link>.
This will cause the window to move until you have released the mouse button.
</para>
<para>
To change the mode that the moving of the windows uses (opaque being the
default), open up the <link linkend="settings">Settings</link> menu, and select "Move &amp; Resize
Settings".  You can select from a list that looks similar to the one here
above-right.  Experiment until you find one that suits you best.
</para>
<para>
For some serious eyecandy, try out the Translucent move mode.  This will only
work if your X server and E16 are running on the same machine,
however.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="resizemode"><title>Resizing Windows</title>
<img src="E_move_resize_settings.png" x="300" y="50"/>
<para>
E16 also comes with several available methods for resizing windows.
You can perform the actual resize on the window by clicking on any
resize-handle of your window <link linkend="border">border</link> and dragging to the desired size.
You can also get the same effect by using the ALT + middle button
<link linkend="mousebind">Mouse Binding</link> in any part of the window.
</para>
<para>
To change the mode that the resizing of the windows uses (opaque being the
default), open up the <link linkend="settings">Settings</link> menu, and select "Move &amp; Resize
Settings".  You can select from a list that looks similar to the one here
above-right.  Experiment until you find one that suits you best.
</para>
<para>
The best eyecandy resize mode is probably technical move mode.  This mode shows
you the height and width of the window, in addition to the distance from the
nearest edge.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="windowops"><title>The Window Operations Menu</title>
<img src="E_app_rightmouse_menu.png" x="360" y="40"/>
<para>
The Window Operations menu is a commonly used menu that allows you to perform
many different actions onto the current window.
</para>
<para>
The Close function closes the window in question.
Annihilate destroys the window without
regard to the application the window belongs to, which is especially useful if
the application refuses to respond to being closed with Close.
</para>
<para>
The Iconify function iconifies the window.
If you have an <link linkend="iconbox">Iconbox</link> it is sent to the nearest one.
</para>
<para>
The Raise function raises the window above any windows
that may be obscuring it and Lower
lowers it below windows it is obscuring.
</para>
<para/>
<para>
(more on next page ...)
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="windowops2"><title/>
<para>
Shade/Unshade toggles the shaded state of the window. Note that borderless
windows are not allowed to be shaded.
</para>
<para>
Stick/Unstick toggles the sticky state of a window. A window that is sticky
remains "stuck to the glass" and thus is visible on all virtual and
multiple <link linkend="desktops">desktops</link>.
</para>
<para>
Fullscreen/Window <link linkend="tut11">zooms</link> in and out of the window changing resolutions
if possible. This feature will only work if you have your X server configured
correctly and it supports the XVidtune extension. Your X server may not like
having resolutions changed - it is possible that an unstable X server could
crash if you use this. Be aware of this when using this feature.
</para>
<para>
Remember... displays the <link linkend="properties">Remember Properties</link> dialog that lets
you select things to remember about this instance of an application. The
attributes selected to be remembered in the state they are when you hit Apply or
Ok in this dialog. You will have to bring it up again if you wish to remember
a new state of the window.
</para>
<para/>
<para>
(more on next page ...)
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="windowops3"><title/>
<para>
In the <link linkend="groups">Window Groups</link> submenu there are various options for
configuring window
groups and how this window relates to any groups you may have.
</para>
<para>
You can quickly modify the size of a window to one of several aspects of
maximum sizes using the Window Size submenu.
</para>
<para>
Set Stacking lets you change the stacking layer of that window.
</para>
<para>
You can change the <link linkend="changeborder">border</link> using the Set Border Style menu if
you wish to use a different window border. If you change themes after you have
changed the border, and the new theme doesn't provide a border of the same
name, the window will fall back to using the DEFAULT border until you
change it again.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="placement"><title>Window Placement and Autoraise</title>
<img src="E_placement_settings.png" x="220" y="70"/>
<img src="E_autoraise_settings.png" x="10" y="270"/>
<para>
These two <link linkend="settings">Settings</link> dialogs allow you to configure various options
for the placement of windows.  The two Dialog window options are for windows
like the ALT+O open URL window in Netscape.  Manual Placement will force you to
use the mouse to position every new window that attempts to map itself.
</para>
<para>
The Autoraise settings Dialog will allow you to set a timer event that causes a
window to automatically raise itself to the foreground after a set time.  You
can enable it here, as well as change the timer.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="eesh"><title>E16 and IPC</title>
<para>
E16 has a fairly interesting IPC system that allows external
applications (such as Eterm) to talk to E16 and both ask for
information and change information.  There is a program that was installed with
E16 called "eesh" that is a simple shell interface to the IPC in
E16.  It's even got its own documentation.  You can go into
eesh and type "help" and it should spit back a list of commands that it
understands.
</para>
<para>
Note: there are many commands that will show up in E's IPC that don't
necessarily work yet, or aren't fully implemented.  You CAN potentially do some
really bizarre things to your system by using eesh, but for the most part it's
just another interesting interface to E.  In your distribution package you
should have received some sample scripts written in Perl that interface to E
through eesh showing how you can externally script E to do more things outside
E's base functionality.  Expect the IPC to flesh out even more in future
revisions.
</para>
<para>
To exit eesh, hit CTRL + D (EOF)
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="editmenus"><title>Editing E16's Menus</title>
<para>
The first time you run E16 as a user after you've installed it, it
should create a directory under your home directory called .e16/menus.  In
this directory, there will be a file called "file.menu" - this file controls
the contents of your left-mouse button <link linkend="rootmenu">Menu</link>.  The very first line
of this file contains the title for the menu, and the remainder of the file
looks something like this:
</para>
<font face="Vera/10" color="#112222"/>
<para>
"Eterm" NULL exec "Eterm"
</para>
<font face="Vera/11" color="#ffffff"/>
<para>
Where each column represents:
</para>
<font face="Vera/10" color="#112222"/>
<para>
Entry title, graphic for menu (or NULL), exec "commandline"
</para>
<font face="Vera/11" color="#ffffff"/>
<para>
You may have several files in here, including a KDE menu and a Gnome menu if
E16 has detected their presence during installation.  If
detected, your primary apps will be located in another file called
user_apps.menu.  Each of these files is for you to edit as desired.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="editkeys"><title>Editing Your Keybindings</title>
<para>
To set your own keybindings, all you have to do is find the bindings.cfg
file that was installed with E16, and make a copy in your
~/.e16 directory. This file shouldn't be too difficult to edit.
Be careful!  The keybindings in this file will override ALL
the default keybindings, as long as this file exists, so edit this file with
extreme caution (unless you know what you're doing).
</para>
<para>
To reset your keybindings back to the default, simply remove this file from
your ~/.e16 directory.  The next time you restart E16
it should reload the default keybindings into memory.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="themes"><title>E16 and Themes</title>
<para>
One of the strong points of E16, of course, is that you can change
around the complete look and feel of your desktop whenever you want to.
Included with the 0.16.8 release are a few themes, to show off a little bit of
this configurability.  You can select them by using the middle mouse button
<link linkend="rootmenu">menu</link>, going to the "Themes" selector, and then choosing a new
theme.  Of course, there are plenty more themes for E16 than come
with it by default.  You can find more by going to:
</para>
<para>
http://e.themes.org
</para>
<para>
and searching around until you find something you like.
</para>
<para>
To install a new theme
is simple: all you need to do is take the bleh.etheme file and drop it into
your ~/.e16/themes directory.  Once you've restarted E16,
it will automatically show up in your Themes <link linkend="rootmenu">menu</link>, and you can
choose it just like any other theme.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="eyecandy"><title>E16's Eyecandy Features</title>
<para>
Of course, E16 wouldn't be complete without just a few bits of
eyecandy to play with.
</para>
<para>
On the "Special FX" <link linkend="settings">settings</link> dialog you can chose two toys:
</para>
<para>
The ripples effect - this causes little ripplets of water to reflect on the
bottom of your screen.
</para>
<para>
The waves effect - similar to ripples, but this one waves up and down as
opposed to side-to-side
</para>
<para>
On the "Desktop Background" <link linkend="settings">settings</link> dialog you can enable "Theme
Transparecy". A slider controls the opacity of the window borders, etc. with
respect to the desktop background.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="maint"><title>Included Maintenance Scripts</title>
<img src="E_maint_menu.png" x="265" y="60"/>
<para>
E16 comes with several scripts that are executable out of the middle
mouse button <link linkend="rootmenu">menu</link> - these scripts can perform all sorts of
maintenance on the files that E16 creates automatically for you.
When you select "Maintenance" you should get a menu that looks something like
the one above-right.  You can also rebuild the menus from here.
</para>
<para>
As a warning, when you purge configuration information, the next time you
restart E16 it will take longer to load.  You can monitor
E16's usage using the query tools provided.  If you change themes a
lot you will probably want to purge the config file cache after you've settled
on a theme.  This will help keep your disk usage by E16 down.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="faq"><title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<para>
<link linkend="faq2">I can't find my iconbox or change its settings.</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faq2">I can't seem to find my left mouse menu.</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faq3">All my settings are mangled and I can't fix it.</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faq3">I upgraded a theme but the new one isn't being used.</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faq4">I set my window to borderless and can't set it back.</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faq4">How can I move or resize the iconbox?</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faq4">How can I disable that annoying desktop tooltip?</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faq5">How can I set up E16 to work with GNOME?</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faq5">How can I set up E16 to work with KDE?</link>
</para>
<para>
<link linkend="faqend">These docs didn't help, where can I get more help?</link>
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="faq2"><title>Frequently Asked Questions: Page 1</title>
<para>
Q: I can't find my <link linkend="iconbox">Iconbox</link> or change its settings.
</para>
<para>
A: There are two possibilities here.
</para>
<para>
1. You don't have an Iconbox on your desktop right now. Just middle-click and
select Desktop/Create new iconbox
</para>
<para>
2. Your Iconbox is transparent and borderless.  Iconify a window and see if
your icon appears.  If so, rightclick on it to reconfigure your Iconbox.
</para>
<para/>
<para>
Q:  I Can't Seem To Find My Left Mouse Menu
</para>
<para>
A:  Your menu files may be destroyed.  Try rerunning the program that initially
generated them.  First you'll want to remove the ~/.e16/menus/*.menu files.
Rebuild them using the <link linkend="maint">Maintenance</link> menu.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="faq3"><title>Frequently Asked Questions: Page 2</title>
<para>
Q:  All My Settings Are Mangled And I Can't Fix It
</para>
<para>
A:  Well, if things get really messed up, you can always remove all of
E16's automatically saved files.  Go into ~/.e16, and
remove the e_config* files, and then blow away the cached directory.
The next time you start E16 it should reset everything to the default.
</para>
<para/>
<para>
Q: I Upgraded My Theme, But The New One Isn't Being Used
</para>
<para>
A: When you upgrade a theme that does not come with E16, when you go
into your ~/.e16/themes directory, be sure to delete the unpacked
directory version of your theme that should be sitting next to the theme, if it
is there.  Otherwise when E16 attempts to start the new version it
will use the old files, which causes this problem.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="faq4"><title>Frequently Asked Questions: Page 3</title>
<para>
Q:  I set my window to borderless and can't set it back or move it.
</para>
<para>
A:  ALT + Right mouse button when pressed anywhere in the window will give you
the <link linkend="windowops">Window Operations</link> menu. ALT + Left mouse button will move the
window and ALT + Middle mouse button will resize the window.
</para>
<para>
Q: How can I move or resize the iconbox?
</para>
<para>
A: As described above, ALT + Right mouse button will give you the
<link linkend="windowops">Window Operations</link> menu, ALT + Middle mouse button will resize the
iconbox and ALT+left mouse button will move it.  See the <link linkend="iconbox">Iconbox</link>
documentation for more help
</para>
<para>
Q: How can I disable that annoying desktop tooltip?
</para>
<para>
A: There is a special config option for it under the <link linkend="tooltips">tooltip</link>
<link linkend="settings">settings</link> menu.
</para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="faq5"><title>Frequently Asked Questions: Page 4</title>
<para>
Q: How do I set up E16 to work with GNOME?
</para>
<para>
A: Start your GNOME session with
</para>
<para><simplelist>
<member>export WINDOW_MANAGER=e16</member>
<member>exec gnome-session</member>
</simplelist></para>
<para/>
<para>
Q: How do I set up E16 to work with KDE?
</para>
<para>
A: Start your KDE session with
</para>
<para><simplelist>
<member>export KDEWM=e16</member>
<member>exec startkde</member>
</simplelist></para>
</refsect2>


<refsect2 id="faqend"><title>Frequently Asked Questions: Page 5</title>
<para>
Q:  These Docs Didn't Help, Where Can I Get More Help?
</para>
<para>
A: Well, we obviously can't answer all of your questions just by predicting
them, so I would try the <link linkend="res">website</link> as well as looking at the
<link linkend="res">mailing lists</link>, especially the mail archives.  Chances are that someone
else has probably had the same problem that you have.  And if all that still
fails, you might try someone on the <link linkend="res">irc</link> channel
</para>
</refsect2>

</refsect1>

 <refsect1 id='for_more_information'><title>FOR MORE INFORMATION</title>
  <para>
   <indexterm><primary>Header</primary><secondary>FOR MORE INFORMATION</secondary></indexterm>
	Please see our web site at <ulink url='http://www.enlightenment.org'>http://www.enlightenment.org</ulink>
  </para>
 </refsect1>
</refentry>
