<chapter id="ch-OjbectHierarchy">
<title>Object Hierarchy</title>

<sect1 id="sec-ObjHierIntro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>
The EWL widgets are setup in a hierarcy. The base widget that everything
extends from is the <literal>Ewl_Object</literal>. The
<literal>Ewl_Object</literal> provides all of the base functionality for
each widget including the sizing, alignment, fill policies, padding and
others. This is the main building block of the EWL. An application using EWL
will never need to allocate an <literal>Ewl_Object</literal>
</para>

<para>
Sitting just above the <literal>Ewl_Object</literal> is the
<literal>Ewl_Widget</literal>. Again, all widgets inheret from this object,
which in turn inherits from the <literal>Ewl_Object</literal>. This object
provides the base functinality for a widget to interact with users. Like
the <literal>Ewl_Object</literal> an application will never need to allocate
an <literal>Ewl_Widget</literal> itself.
</para>

<para>
With the <literal>Ewl_Widget</literal> in place we can start to build up the
hierarchy of widgets that form the EWL. The hierarchy looks something similar to
that in the <link linkend="fig-obj_hierarchy">EWL Object Hierarcy</link> figure below.
</para>

<para>
 <figure id="fig-obj_hierarchy">
  <title>The EWL Object Hierarchy</title>
  <inlinemediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="img/obj_hierarchy.png" format="png" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <phrase>The EWL Object Hierarchy</phrase>
   </textobject>
  </inlinemediaobject>
 </figure>
</para>

<para>
The <literal>Ewl_Container</literal> object is built off of the
<literal>Ewl_Widget</literal> object and provides the functionality for
widgets that are to hold other widgets. This includes anything from the main
window, to boxes, to scrollpanes.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="sec-ObjHierCasting">
<title>Object Casting</title>
<para>
As you progress into EWL you will notice that there is a lot of casting
between different types. To make this easier, each cast to a particular type
has a EWL_TYPE() macro defined. So for example there are EWL_OBJECT(o) and
EWL_WIDGET(o) defined to make life easier.
</para>

<para>
These macros should always be used when converting between EWL widgets so
that you know that the right thing is being done.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="sec-ObjHierNewWidget">
<title>Adding new widgets</title>
<para>
To add new widgets into EWL you just need to create a new struct that has
the appropriate type of subclass as the first element. This subclass object
must not be a pointer.
</para>

<example>
 <title>Creating EWL Widgets</title>
 <programlisting>
struct Ewl_Foo {
    Ewl_Container container;
    int bar;
}
 </programlisting>
</example>
<para>
This would create a new Ewl_Foo widget that inherits from the
<literal>Ewl_Container</literal> so you would be able to pack other widgets
into this new widget type.
</para>
</sect1>

</chapter>

