<chapter>
    <title>Book Overview</title>

<para>In the following paragraphs I will present a brief explanation of the
      contents of each chapter and section. Section titles are emphasized while
      Chapter titles are strongly emphasized.</para>
      
<!-- New Chapter -->

<formalpara>
    <title>I. Structure of a graphical application</title>
    Looking at the code of some of the many open source applications available,
    we can find common components in their structure. This chapter introduces
    the concept of a Event loop and how does it deal with the interaction
    between the functionality and the interface.
</formalpara>

<para>
    <emphasis>I.I. Decomposing the frontend.</emphasis>
    There are different approaches to the creation of Graphical User
    Interfaces, some provide more flexibility while others development speed. In
    any case, the end product will make available the same mechanisms to the
    rest of the application.
</para>

<!-- New Chapter -->

<formalpara>
    <title>II. Introduction to Edje</title>
    Edje is a compromise between flexibility and development time. Comparing it
    to a plain canvas or a fully featured toolkit can show us how it fits in a
    comfortable middle ground with advantages for designers and developers
    alike.
</formalpara>

<para>
    <emphasis>II.I. The foundations.</emphasis>
    Edje allows low level control of the interface without forcing the
    developer through a low level API. The interface objects are implemented as
    Evas objects, but through a completely new language friendly to designers
    and independent from the application code.
</para>

<para>
    <emphasis>II.II.Convenient functions.</emphasis>
    To load an Edje interface the application needs to setup an Evas canvas
    first. This would look as a burden for the developer, dealing with issues
    specific to the underlying system. Thankfully Evas is supported by an
    additional library that resolve most of these issues, Ecore.
</para>

<!-- New Chapter -->

<formalpara>
    <title>III. The foundations in practice</title>
    A practical example of setting up an Evas canvas with the simplest
    approach, Ecore_Evas. 
</formalpara>

<para>
    <emphasis>III.I Working with the canvas.</emphasis>
    Including new Edje objects inside the previously setup canvas can be
    explained with this simple example.
</para>

<para>
    <emphasis>III.II Interacting with the objects.</emphasis>
    There are different channels for the application to interact with the
    interface. For the sake of brevity I will include an example of each one to
    serve as an introduction for the practical examples to come in the next
    chapters.
</para>

<!-- New Chapter -->

<formalpara>
    <title>IV. Introduction to widgets</title>
    Interfaces need to resolve two problems, presenting information to users
    and taking orders from them. The past chapters presented enough information
    to solve the first. In the following chapters we will review the second.
    The widget itself can be seen as a small application inside our interfaces.
    As an example let's examine the structure of a common widget, the combox.
</formalpara>

<para>
    <emphasis>IV.I. The common widget design.</emphasis>
    Revisar el diseño de los widget combox en varias librerias, mostrar las
    pattern usadas y concluir porque MVC es la mejor (si es que lo es).
</para>

<!--<para>
    <emphasis>IV.II. Widget design with Edje</emphasis>
    If the Model View Controller pattern is the choice for developing
    a widget the place Edje ocuppies becomes quite clear. Mostrar el papel
    que ocupa Edje, Ecore_Evas y Ecore_ en cada parte del diseño del widget.
</para>

<para>
    <emphasis>IV.III. The Enlightenment Widget Library</emphasis>
    Añadir una introduccion a EWL y añadir mi vision sobre como debeira ser
    usado en conjunto con Edje destacando claramente que es una opinion
    personal.
</para>

<para>
    <emphasis>IV.III. The Enlightenment ToolKit</emphasis>
    Añadir una introduccion a ETK y añadir mi vision sobre como debeira ser
    usado en conjunto con Edje destacando claramente que es una opinion
    personal.
</para>-->

<!-- New Chapter -->

<formalpara>
    <title>V. The first application, Edje Analyzer</title>
    In this chapter we will create a simple Edje application to view and
    interact with any Edje theme file. This section presents and explains the
    "main()" function along with the global variables and function prototypes.
</formalpara>

<para>
    <emphasis>V.I. The first widget, the window.</emphasis>
    As we know, creating a window is not as simple as we would hope. This
    chapter introduces a method to offload window settings and interface layout
    to an Edje object.
</para>

<para>
    <emphasis>V.I.I. Developer, meet SWALLOW parts.</emphasis>
    Edje provies a simple yet very powerful method to layout the components of
    an interface. This is a simple introduction to the concept.
</para>

<para>
    <emphasis>V.I.II. Designer, meet GROUP parts.</emphasis>
    A note about the additional uses for Edje groups that both designer and
    developer should be aware off.
</para>

<section>
    <title>Useful resources</title>

    <para>
        Before we begin I would list a collection of books and articles that
        I found critical for learning about the Enlightenment Foundation
        Libraries.
            
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="http://docs.enlightenment.org/api/edje/htm">
                <citetitle>The Edje API Reference</citetitle> by Carsten
                Haitzler.</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="http://docs.enlightenment.org/books/edjebook/edjebook.pdf">
                <citetitle>Building Interfaces with Edje: The Edje Developers
                Guide</citetitle> by Ben Rockwood.</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="http://docs.enlightenment.org/books/cookbook/eflcookbook.html">
                <citetitle>The EFL Cookbook</citetitle> by several authors.</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="http://homepages.pathfinder.gr/kazanaki/contrib/">
                <citetitle>Introduction to the Enlightenment foundation
                libraries</citetitle> by Kostis Kapelonis.</ulink>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <ulink url="http://rephorm.com/pages/tutorials/evas/toc">
                <citetitle>Evas Tutorials</citetitle> by rephorm</ulink>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>

</chapter>
